A Guide to the Samuel Pannill Wilson Papers 1847-1938
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Samuel Pannill Wilson Papers 1847-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10721
ca. 765 items
This collection consists of ca. 765 items, reflecting the varied financial and legal activities of Samuel Pannill Wilson, a Pittsylvania County, Virginia plantation owner.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Joseph M. Whitehead of Chatham, Virginia, through Mr. Herman Melton, on May 27, 1987.
Scope and Content Information
These papers consist of ca. 765 items, 1847-(1860-1899)-1938, and reflect the varied financial and legal activities of Samuel Pannill Wilson of Pittsylvania County, Virginia. It includes indentures, accounts, letters, receipts, promissory notes, tax receipts, and other related papers concerning Wilson's plantation and his personal and financial obligations. The majority of his dealings took place in Danville (Pittsylvania County) and other Virginia locales including Patrick, Henry, and Rockingham counties and the cities of Martinsville and Richmond, and in North Carolina.
There are several items pertaining to blacks: bill for a medical visit to a sick slave girl, February 1861; list of Negroes treated by Dr. Robert A. Read, October 6, 1858 and by Dr. J. O'Leary, November 4, 1862; list of wages paid to blacks (sharecroppers?), May 1867; taxes paid on slaves; receipts for slaves (Cornelius, Charles, Peter, Harrison, and Gil Bass) who had been impressed to work on Confederate fortifications, 1863-1864; and Freedman's Bureau indenture for the apprenticeship of two brothers, Farrel and Edmond Wilson, in order to learn farming skills, December 1, 1865. A blank Bureau contract form, ca. 1865, is also present.
Items of special interest include materials regarding the expenses of Ruth Wilson as a student at the Roanoke Female and Thomasville(?) Female colleges, 1870-1878 & 1880; a receipt for taxes paid on two gold watches, May 26, 1869; various tax payments to Confederate authorities, 1863-1865; a right-of-way agreement and a list of damages to Wilson's plantation by the Danville & New River Railroad Company, November 10, 1880 and May 16, 1881; and wages paid to an overseer, William R. Winn, March 22, 1862. Also of interest are items pertaining to building material purchases, tobacco transactions, Danville banks, grist mills, Southern Express Company invoices, a 1909 survey of a house tract, and an undated receipt showing Wilson's payment of three bushels of corn for a suit of clothes.
Contents List
- Miscellaneous Financial and Legal Papers 1847, 1848, 1856-1899, 1938, n.d., 7 folders; 461 items (Box 1)
- Medical Expenses 1858-1875, 1881, 8 items (Box 1)
- Building Material Purchases 1860-1862, 1872, 16 items (Box 1)
- Danville & New River Railroad Receipts 1861-1887, 19 items (Box 1)
- Wages Paid (chiefly to Negroes) 1861-1883, 43 items (Box 2)
- Tax Receipts 1861-1892, 50 items (Box 2)
- Letters 1861-1896, 1937, 12 items (Box 2)
- Confederate Transactions 1862-1865, 25 items (Box 2)
- Danville, Virginia Banks 1867-1887, 35 items (Box 2)
- Tobacco Transactions 1867, 1871-1887, 45 items (Box 2)
- Roanoke Female College: Expenses for Ruth Wilson 1870-1878, 1880, 22 items (Box 2)
- Grist Mill Papers 1871-1878, 1885, 12 items (Box 2)
- Southern Express Company Invoices 1871-1882, 13 items (Box 2)
- Survey of a house tract 1909, 1 item (Box 2)